<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!--
Copyright 2004-2005 The Apache Software Foundation

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<document>

	<properties>
		<author email="nicko at apache dot org">Nicko Cadell</author>
		<title>Building log4net</title>
	</properties>

	<meta name="keywords" content="building log4net, log4net" />

	<body>
		<section name="Building log4net">
			<sectionMenu name="Contents" />
			
			<p>
				The log4net release builds are built using NAnt. Log4net can also be built
				using Visual Studio .NET 2002 or 2003.
			</p>
			<p>
				To build a release build of log4net you will need to create a strong
				name key file. See the Strong Name section below. 
			</p>
		
			<section name="Visual Studio .NET" id="id_1">
				<p>
					Visual Studio .NET 2002 and 2003 are supported build platforms for log4net.
				</p>

				<section name="Visual Studio .NET 2002" id="id_2">
					<p>
						The log4net distribution includes a solution and project file
						for Visual Studio .NET 2002. Open the <span class="code">log4net.sln</span>
						from the src directory in the distribution.
					</p>
					<p>
						The log4net project requires only the following references:
					</p>
					<ul>
						<li>System</li>
						<li>System.Data</li>
						<li>System.Web</li>
						<li>System.XML</li>
					</ul>
				</section>

				<section name="Visual Studio .NET 2003" id="id_3">
					<p>
						Open the Visual Studio .NET 2002 solution file as above. 
						Visual Studio will convert the solution and project files
						to Visual Studio .NET 2003 format.
					</p>
					<p>
						The log4net project file is not suitable for building log4net
						for the .NET Compact Framework. To build for the Compact Framework
						you must create a new C# project for Smart Devices. Configure the
						project as a library project. Add all the C# files from the 
						src directory in the distribution.
					</p>
				</section>
			</section>
			
			<section name="NAnt">
				<p>
					The log4net distribution is built using the NAnt tool.
					NAnt version 0.85 is required to build log4net, it is 
					available from <a href="http://nat.sourceforge.net">nant.sourceforge.net</a>.
				</p>
				<p>
					To support building log4net for the SSCLI framework the NAnt configuration
					files need to be updated to specify the SSCLI framework directory.
				</p>
				<p>
					To build log4net from the command line, change directory to the root of the
					log4net distribution, ensure that the nant executable is in the
					PATH, and then run the following command:
				</p>
				<div class="syntax"><pre class="code">
nant -buildfile:log4net.build compile-all</pre></div>
				<p>
					This command will build log4net for all the supported frameworks
					that are available on the current machine. To list all the build
					targets that are available run the following command:
				</p>
				<div class="syntax"><pre class="code">
nant -buildfile:log4net.build -projecthelp</pre></div>
				<p>
					Under windows the <span class="code">build.cmd</span> can be used 
					to script the nant build. This can be called from a different
					directory and will locate the correct log4net.build file to use.
					For example:
				</p>
				<div class="syntax"><pre class="code">
build.cmd compile-all</pre></div>
			</section>

			<section name="Strong Name">
				<p>
					In order to build the Release builds of log4net a Strong
					Name key is required. 
				</p>
				<p>
					Use the <span class="code">sn.exe</span> tool in the 
					.NET Framework SDK to generate a strong name key pair.
				</p>
				<div class="syntax"><pre class="code">
sn -k log4net.snk</pre></div>
				<p>
					The log4net.snk file should be placed in the root of the
					log4net distribution, in the same folder as the log4net.build
					file.
				</p>
			</section>

			<section name="SDK Reference">
				<p>
					NDoc is used to build the log4net SDK documentation.
					NDoc is available from <a href="http://ndoc.sourceforge.net">ndoc.sourceforge.net</a>.
				</p>
			</section>

			<section name="HTML Documentation">
				<p>
					The log4net HTML documentation is built using Velocity.
					The source are XML files in the <span class="code">xdcos/src</span> directory.
					Building the documentation requires Java, Ant, and Velocity.
					Run ant from within the <span class="code">xdocs</span> directory.
				</p>
			</section>

		</section>
	</body>
</document>
